<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Voyageur Technologique</title>
    <link>http://example.org/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Voyageur Technologique</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://example.org/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/hello/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/hello/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Look at this content! So exciting!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Entrepreneurial State</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2017-05-09-Book-Review-The-Entrepreneurial-State/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2017-05-09-Book-Review-The-Entrepreneurial-State/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was first getting interested in Cognitive Science, I started reading “How to Build a Brain” by Chris Eliasmith. By the end of it, I truly felt biologically plausible modelling was hugely important for the advance of Cognitive Science. I also knew this feeling was misleading given I had no familiarity of the argument landscape. Why wasn’t everyone else doing biologically plausible modelling? Why were they still using their seemingly inferior frameworks? It took me three years, a conference, part of my master’s degree, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cogsci.stackexchange.com/users/4397/seanny123?tab=questions&#34;&gt;more than a hundred questions on CogSci.SE&lt;/a&gt; and multiple blog posts to figure out satisfactory answers to those questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, after reading “&lt;a href=&#34;https://marianamazzucato.com/entrepreneurial-state/&#34;&gt;The Entrepreneurial State: debunking public vs. private sector myths&lt;/a&gt;” by Dr. Mazzucato, I feel the same way, but I don’t have three years to dedicate to it’s investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central thesis of The Entrepreneurial State is that government funded research drives the economy of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state is able to fund foundational technological research and bring it to market. The government does this in ways that venture capital and industry is unable, despite the opposite is usually thought of as common knowledge. It is able to do this due to it’s size. It’s able to absorb the risk long-term landscape using funding organisation like via funding organisation and developmental banks such as DARPA, NIH and ARPA-e. Examples of countries currently doing this successfully are Germany and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This basic research is one of the core drivers of the economy, thus it takes priority over controlling deficits of spending. However consideration is given to how the government gets this money. Mazzucato argues the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/thomas_piketty_new_thoughts_on_capital_in_the_twenty_first_century&#34;&gt;taxation reforms put forth by Piketty&lt;/a&gt; are insufficient given the ease of tax evasion. Consequently, the government must tax the use of the technologies it creates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mazzucato gives multiple examples of the importance of basic research being funded by the government. Specifically, the IT revolution, drug development and the Green revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The section on the IT revolution focuses on Apple and how every aspect of their products, from integrated circuits, small form-factor hard-drives and touch screens to the software behind Siri, were funded by government initiatives. Consequently, Apple’s “innovation” lies in synthesizing products after all the hard research has been done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Green Revolution section more generally gives a tour of various attempts at solar/wind energy and how government support differentiated companies (Vestas, Kenetech and Tesla) who fell versus those who succeeded after temporary setbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the counter-arguments I’ve found boil down to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The effect of “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/116937?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&#34;&gt;crowding out&lt;/a&gt;” needs to be taken into greater account. Basically, R&amp;amp;D personnel are a finite resource and government funding consumes the supply of talent unproductively compared to the private sector. This ties interestingly into the idea of there being &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/i-m-h-o/stem-still-no-shortage-c6f6eed505c1&#34;&gt;no shortage of STEM graduates, but a glaring shortage of competent people&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pricesandmarkets.org/volume-3-issue-3-winter-2015/mariana-mazzucato-the-entrepreneurial-state/&#34;&gt;A statistic was mis-interpreted in an argument in the book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The critic didn’t read the book, but doesn’t like what it’s implying. Consequently, instead of critique the arguments, they’re going to argue semantics to death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links to well thought-out criticisms, particularly in peer-reviewed journals, would be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the book is masterfully written, but it raises more questions than it answers. What does a good developmental bank look like? Why are the DARPA folks so good at determining when to pull out of a bad investment? How does a government know when it has committed sufficient amount of funding? How does a government know if the distribution of spending is adequate? Can all of these goals be accomplished transparently? When are shareholder buy-backs reasonable and not a sign of a dysfunctional economy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I supposed my inability to answer these questions is due to the fact I am neither a politician, nor an economist. However, recommendations for further reading to answer these questions would be appreciated. Until then, you’ll probably be finding me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://economics.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;Economics.SE&lt;/a&gt; in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked this post, consider joining&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://eepurl.com/cOiPPD&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;my mailing list&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;to get updated about future posts like this one after I leave Medium.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StackExchange for Open Science</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2017-04-28-StackExchange-for-Open-Science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2017-04-28-StackExchange-for-Open-Science/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-it-s-worth-answering-your-own-questions-in-public&#34;&gt;Why it’s worth answering your own questions in public&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time you have to figure something out, to make sure you understand it, leave a question/answer pair on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://stackexchange.com/sites#science-traffic&#34;&gt;relevant StackExchange&lt;/a&gt;. Why? I’LL TELL YOU WHY!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;you-re-helping-yourself-the-most&#34;&gt;You’re helping yourself the most&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You take notes anyways and the best way to remember something is to restructure the knowledge you’re trying to store. Might as well write the notes in public so other people can read them and jump in on your trail of reasoning. And by “other people”, I include your future self who’s forgotten you even had the question in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;it-will-make-you-a-better-writer&#34;&gt;It will make you a better writer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the difference between a good writer and a bad one is how much feedback they’ve gotten. On StackExchange, &lt;a href=&#34;https://meta.stackexchange.com/help/editing&#34;&gt;people are incentivized to suggest edits to your question&lt;/a&gt;. These edits are reviewed by the community, so it’s common to revisit your question later and find it greatly improved, along with explanations of the improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;everyone-will-be-nice&#34;&gt;Everyone will be nice&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meta.stackexchange.com/help/be-nice&#34;&gt;Or we’ll kick them out&lt;/a&gt;. StackExchange has excellent moderation tools and &lt;em&gt;elected&lt;/em&gt; moderators. This means the community is always being led by it’s most enthusiastic members, not just the bitter old people who’ve been around the longest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;shorter-easier-than-a-blog-post&#34;&gt;Shorter/easier than a blog post&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blog posts are hard. You have to consider an intended audience, a scope and a structure. With StackExchange, all of these choices are made for you. The audience is other people looking for the answers to the same question. The scope depends on the StackExchange site. The structure is a short question and answer. I’ve written maybe 20 blogs posts, but I’ve written almost &lt;a href=&#34;https://cogsci.stackexchange.com/users/4397/seanny123?tab=profile&#34;&gt;200 questions and answers&lt;/a&gt;, because it’s so much easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;direct-feedback&#34;&gt;Direct feedback&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my blog, I get two metrics: visits and comments. With a question, I get to know if I helped someone else by visits, but also upvotes. I get to be notified if my answer has become out of date with comments left by other users. I get to know if my answer wasn’t as complete as it could have been, by reading other answers to the same question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try it. Be one of the first 20 people to ask 5 upvoted questions on one of &lt;a href=&#34;https://stackexchange.com/sites#science-traffic&#34;&gt;the science StackExchange sites&lt;/a&gt; (starting from the date of this blog post) and I’ll give 5 dollars to the charity of your choice. Send me a link to your profile with your linked Twitter profile via Twitter as proof. If you’re having a tough time or it isn’t working for you, talk to me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>List: Tools I love and hate</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2017-04-16-List-Tools-I-love-and-hate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2017-04-16-List-Tools-I-love-and-hate/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;No one wants to read a series of blog posts about the various tools I use on a daily basis and how I feel about them. But maybe someone wants to read one blog post? Here it is in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;love&#34;&gt;Love&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bandcamp&lt;/strong&gt; You let me buy and download music for all my favourite artists and then you get the hell out of my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MindMup&lt;/strong&gt; You’re still the only mind-mapping solution that works for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TagSpaces&lt;/strong&gt; You make my research make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pocket&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks for helping me realize that most articles I think I want to read, I actually only want to read at the time because I’m bored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CamScanner&lt;/strong&gt; When just signing a PDF isn’t acceptable, you enable me to not going on a hunt for someone who still owns a printer/scanner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TrulyErgonomic Keyboard&lt;/strong&gt; The gateway drug of ergonomic keyboards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hate&#34;&gt;Hate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Android&lt;/strong&gt; Who do I have to kill to get a phone that is regularly updated? Also, can we please get a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.cryptographyengineering.com/2016/11/24/android-n-encryption/&#34;&gt;secure system&lt;/a&gt; with the next version?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Itunes&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t need you to sync, I need you to let me drop in a folder into my file-system and for you to discover it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/strong&gt; Why the hell do I have to download a package to get sane power management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Windows&lt;/strong&gt; I know you’re super-secure and you’re still the OS I trust my grandfather with, but you’ve made it impossible to move a window between virtual desktops with a keyboard shortcut. For this I will never forgive you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PDFs&lt;/strong&gt; I know why you exist, but it doesn’t make me hate you any less. You make me have to use other tools like pdfgrep just to search through you and you’re stunting the progress of scientific communication.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thing Explainer: Spaun</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2017-04-16-Thing-Explainer-Spaun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2017-04-16-Thing-Explainer-Spaun/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[epistemic status: poorly written, potentially missing the point and desperately in need of some figures]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I found a lab’s blog that explained everything using only &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/thing-explainer/&#34;&gt;the 1000 most common words in the English language in the manner popularised by XKCD&lt;/a&gt;. I thought I would try to do it for my lab’s philosophy/research and see how far I got. Also, because I frequently send my papers to my parents and I’m pretty sure they don’t understand anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/338/6111/1202&#34;&gt;We built something like a brain using a computer!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to make something that’s like-a-brain in a computer for many reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because when you put a like-a-brain in a computer you can try to make it do different things, that would be mean or take to much time/money to do, to people who have real brains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, people have been trying to make very-good-at-thinking computers for a while and they did a pretty good job. We have computers that are very good at one thing-that-people-are-good-at. But no computers that are good at a lots of things-that-people-are-good-at. Also, no computers take what they learned from one thing and use what they learned to many other things. We think to do this type of learning we should build like-a-brains for computers, since we’re trying to make computers be like humans who are using their real brains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;is-it-a-good&#34;&gt;Is it a good?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s okay. A perfect like-a-brain would be exactly like a brain. Ours is kind of like a brain. It’s close in some ways and far in other ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check if your like-a-brain is good, you have to ask questions like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can it do the same things human brains do? Does it do the same things in the same human-like ways?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does it get the same things wrong that people do?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we read from your like-a-brain in the same way we read from real brains in hospitals, do we read the same thing?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see if it’s actually a good like-a-brain, your one like-a-brain should do a lot of different things. Because real brains do a lot of different things. But most like-a-brains only do one thing. This is bad. Our brain does a lot of different things. It can read and draw numbers. It can do simple number problems. It can solve some other problems usually used to check how good people are at thinking. It does these things the same way humans do them. So our like-a-brain is okay, but it’s not great because it can’t do that many things yet. We need to keep working to build a better like-a-brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we built a good like-a-brain, then we should also read stuff from it. We can read stuff from our like-a-brain, because we built it with something close to actual brain-parts. Actual brain-parts are tiny things joined to each other by lines they use for talking. They talk with these lines by sending pointed waves down the lines. We imitated actual brain-parts. We read from the brain-parts. Our like-a-brain brain-parts were like a real brain brain-parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those brain-parts also do other good things like they’re very good at working together even if some of the brain-parts die or get hurt and they use very little food. Using very little food is important for computers that move around and are not plugged in, because they need to take their computer-food with them and carrying computer-food is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing about using good like-brain-parts is that we can do things to our like-a-brain that we talked about before, like give get-not-sick-food or hurt. Then we can tell people who have the same brain-hurt what to do to get better, given what we saw the like-a-brain do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you know why we built a like-a-brain and why we think our like-a-brain is good. But how did we build the like-a-brain?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math. Lots of math. So much math. Years of math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked this article and want to read more of my brain science posts, consider&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://uwaterloo.us15.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=d5612fe997cc72aac70c4ffe9&amp;amp;id=76226838bc&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;subscribing to my mailing list&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Basics of Non-Violent Communication</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2017-02-26-The-Basics-of-Non-Violent-Communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2017-02-26-The-Basics-of-Non-Violent-Communication/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[epistemic status: basic overview of a useful concept from an amateur, as opposed to the exhaustive description provided by&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonviolent_Communication?oldformat=true&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;the excellently written Wikipedia article&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or the various books on the topic]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are an unavoidable part of life. Humans have a natural tendency to want to be with other people and we often need help to pursue things we value. So you’d think we would have developed a better way of working together that didn’t usually end up with people getting angry and hurt, or worse never being able to feel connected to anyone you’re around at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marshall Rosenberg tried to fix our ability to understand each other. He developed this system called Non-Violent Communication (NVC), which he used in a ton of different conflict situations, ranging from couples therapy to negotiating peace between warring groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-Violent Communication tells you a way of modelling and interacting with human beings in a peaceful and productive matter. It models human beings as having needs and needing empathy. When these needs get violated, emotions like anger and sadness arise. There are some basic needs that everyone shares, like food, water and sleep. There are other basic needs that might vary subjectively from person to person, but are still easy to relate to, like the need for beauty and order. Below are some examples I’ve adapted from “Living Nonviolent Communication: Practical Tools to Connect and Communicate Skillfully in Every Situation” by Marshall Rosenberg:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical Nurturance&lt;/strong&gt; Rest, food/water, air, shelter, touch, protection from life-threatening danger, movement/exercise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autonomy&lt;/strong&gt; Choosing your dreams, goals and values, as well as how you plan to achieve or work towards them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Celebration and Public Expression&lt;/strong&gt; Sharing the joy of a dream fulfilled or a life created. Publicly expressing the sadness of losing someone you love or being rejected from an opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt; Acceptance, appreciation, honesty allowing us to learn from limitations, consideration, respect, support, trust, understanding, emotional safety, empathy, warmth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Play&lt;/strong&gt; Fun, laughter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract values&lt;/strong&gt; Beauty, order, harmony, peace, inspiration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that human beings have needs, when you are interacting with someone who is angry or sad, you should try to address those needs directly. Wrong! You’re probably going to end up misunderstanding them. There are a lot of needs and Marshall people need their emotions addressed before they can introspect to identify their own needs. Peaceful interaction comes from showing empathy by acknowledging feelings and then trying to address needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the process can be broken down as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  Adapted from the same book mentioned previously ([source](https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1MCkHBxkqJ8jPAFKiX5iDSeeXuMUTDBV--b8rf0wDUwY/edit?usp=sharing))
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/The-Basics-of-Non-Violent-Communication_0.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems simple enough, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://rest-is-rust.tumblr.com/post/152198686610/notes-from-nonviolent-communication&#34;&gt;there are some pitfalls to avoid&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blame&lt;/strong&gt; Ourselves or others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Judgement&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t make a global description of the person or yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Denial of Responsibility&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t attribute things to outside factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demands&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t force actions on others, try to find a mutually beneficial action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad Listening&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t give advice, story-tell, shut-down the conversation with platitudes, console, pity, interrogate or correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;examples&#34;&gt;Examples&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite example comes from Marshall’s peace-keeping work, which I’ve adapted below from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inquiringmind.com/Articles/Peacemaker.html&#34;&gt;one of his interviews&lt;/a&gt;. Try to see how the four steps noted above are used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About eight years ago, I was mediating between a Muslim tribe and a Christian tribe in northern Nigeria. In their conflict, a quarter of the population had been killed. At that time, they were fighting about how many places in the marketplace each side would have to display their products. I started the reconciliation process with them by saying that I was confident that if we could hear each other’s needs, we could find a way to get everybody’s needs met. Inviting whoever wanted to start, I asked: “What needs of yours are not getting met?” The chief from the Christian tribe screamed, “You people are murderers!” Notice that when I asked him what needs weren’t getting met, his response was to tell me what was wrong with the other side. This provoked a counter judgement. Somebody on the Muslim side screamed back, “You’ve been trying to dominate us! We’re not going to tolerate it any more!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because our training is based on the assumption that all violent language is a tragic expression of unmet needs, when the chiefs finished screaming, my job was to translate the enemy image of “murderer” into language describing the needs of the person who screamed. I said, “Chief, are you saying that your need for safety is not being met and you want some agreement that no matter what the conflict, that it be resolved some way other than violence?” He looked shocked for a moment because this is different from how people are trained to think. Then he said, “That’s exactly right!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But getting the chief to acknowledge his need wasn’t enough. I had to get the Muslim side to see through their enemy image. I said, “Would somebody on the other side please tell me what you heard the chief say his needs were?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gentleman from the Muslim tribe screamed back, “Then why did you kill my son?” In fact, there were several others in the Muslim tribe who knew that someone present had killed one of their children. So there were a lot of feelings. The Muslim tribe had to put down their rage long enough to hear the needs of the Christian tribe. And that wasn’t easy. I had to give them some empathy before they could do that. But finally I got them to hear just one simple thing, that the Christian tribe had said they had a need for safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me about an hour and a half to get both sides to release the enemy image long enough to hear a need of the other side. At that point, one of the chiefs came up and said to me, “If we know how to communicate this way, we don’t have to kill each other!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see how the steps of observation (obvious hostility between the groups), feelings (vocalising feelings and making sure each party is actually hearing them), needs (need for safety and independence) and omitted requests/suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you live in a conflict zone, you’re probably going to need to find different ways of going through this process that feel more natural to you. This being a personal journey, I can’t really advise on how to do this, but I can say that it does take practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;appendix-similar-philosophies&#34;&gt;Appendix: Similar Philosophies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to find similarities between Non-Violent Communication and other philosophies. The need to see another person’s needs instead of just labelling them, is similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20160707223916/http://johngreenbooks.com:80/a-speech-i-wrote-for-the-alan-conference/&#34;&gt;John Green’s request to imagine people complexly&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, needs and their connection to emotions are quite similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@edelwax/what-are-feelings-d54a741ea134#.qgjifho4g&#34;&gt;the values and their connection to emotion&lt;/a&gt; espoused by Joe Edelman’s value-based &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@edelwax/nothing-to-be-done-bfe2ce71a3a2#.8xfp0sfs9&#34;&gt;design culture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning is almost the brain</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2017-01-09-Deep-Learning-is-almost-the-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2017-01-09-Deep-Learning-is-almost-the-brain/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;and-it-s-results-still-look-like-one-sometimes&#34;&gt;(and it’s results still look like one sometimes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[epistemic status: an update on a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/deep-learning-isnt-the-brain-e1d800ebb5a9#.qkv2fs6ah&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;previous position&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;as a result of discussion with people smarter than me]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People emailed me and I read their stuff! As I predicted, I was sometimes horribly wrong and often too simplistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  It currently has 800 views, which is 10 times more than my usual readership.
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/Deep-Learning-is-almost-the-brain_0.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an update/clarification on my positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;some-form-of-back-prop-could-be-biologically-plausible&#34;&gt;Some form of back-prop could be biologically plausible&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;a href=&#34;http://cogsci.stackexchange.com/q/16269/4397&#34;&gt;a ton of work&lt;/a&gt; on biologically plausible back-prop and it was really unfair of me to dismiss them all in one paragraph. That being said, I’m still sceptical of the various implementations, due to the fact they seem to exist in isolation of each other and I can’t find any of their code anywhere (except for “&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1610.00161&#34;&gt;Deep learning with segregated dendrites&lt;/a&gt;”) so I can evaluate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;against-theoretical-isolation-a-manifesto&#34;&gt;Against theoretical isolation: a manifesto&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new, much better informed position on DL is that I wish it didn’t exist in such isolation. &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@seanaubin/understanding-the-brain-where-metaphors-limit-you-13d5d5fbdc57#.9fw8ikmog&#34;&gt;As I’ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, I think a promising line of research is integrating it with other approaches to cognitive modelling. If there was some way it was possible to move up and down the ladder of abstraction with DL, I would consider it a much better analogy for neural computation. Additionally, this would resolve the other weaker arguments (about DL not leveraging biological details, the limitations of current neuromorphic hardware and the lack of spike use in learning) from my previous post. Finally, this would also allow for the leveraging of the powerful developmental explanations allowed by DL by other cognitive modelling paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  The Cognitive Modelling [Ladder of Abstraction](http://worrydream.com/LadderOfAbstraction/). ([image source](https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1mknlMUpnFzRXpb3L_dt-x8hxYK42b1pxlNfYstDH8uc/edit?usp=sharing))
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/Deep-Learning-is-almost-the-brain_0.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realise this is a purely philosophical position about what a good future for cognitive modelling looks like. I’m sure there are detractors who consider it unnecessary to connect to different approaches via biology. However I feel like a lack of synthesis can lead to overly complicated, unscalable models. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;http://compneuro.uwaterloo.ca/publications/crawford2015.html&#34;&gt;Eric Crawford’s model of knowledge representation&lt;/a&gt;, which demonstrated how using symbols and neurons allows for much more scalable model than a purely neural approach. Alternatively, consider &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/338/6111/1202&#34;&gt;Spaun&lt;/a&gt;. It is only able to perform many tasks and generate many predictions as a result of mixing different approaches which would only be possible with a much greater increase in complexity. However these are feelings, not facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  ([source](https://twitter.com/umruehren/status/816665138161799168))
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/Deep-Learning-is-almost-the-brain_1.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way I can see my philosophy can be proved wrong is if cognitive modelling advances without consulting biology. In which case I will abandon my pretences and join everyone in the realm of pure mathematics. Until then I’ll keep trying to build my ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This philosophical approach isn’t easy and I’m sure others have attempted this. I’m just not clear on why the other attempts failed. Is it a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@seanaubin/the-surprising-things-i-learned-from-grad-school-8a0efd458ae0#.94hfg15yq&#34;&gt;lack of reproducible computational experiments due to various problems&lt;/a&gt;? Or was it just too difficult until now? I look forward to working to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked this article and want to read more of my brain science posts, consider&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://uwaterloo.us15.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=d5612fe997cc72aac70c4ffe9&amp;amp;id=76226838bc&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;subscribing to my mailing list&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Value of Thinking Programmatically: Another Apology</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2016-12-02-The-Value-of-Thinking-Programmatically-Another-Apology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2016-12-02-The-Value-of-Thinking-Programmatically-Another-Apology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[epistemic status: an explainer for why people are excited about kids learning programming for people who don’t know programming. Probably&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/humane-tech/its-more-than-just-teach-kids-to-code-177fd6cb7184#.82ep4vtvy&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;written about elsewhere more eloquently&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes listen to podcasts when I’m doing boring programming. The other day I was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=upsQwlVunVw&amp;amp;list=PLV_qemO0oatjBdU5rfC8-gM9t4Trgwg9n&amp;amp;index=5&#34;&gt;listening to a podcast of people describing their first computer experiences&lt;/a&gt;. They talked about having a room at school full of Macintoshes with Hypercard loaded on them, but those computers being rarely used and then carted away before being replace by some other machine without an interface for a usable introduction to thinking programmatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made me realize that for the last 25 years, we’ve had computer capable of teaching kids to program cool things and yet we’ve hardly ever used them. This made me really sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I remembered that I had recently visited my old High School where I literally ended up &lt;em&gt;begging&lt;/em&gt; the computer science teacher to let me design a curriculum for him. The students were progressing through CSS and HTML (alright, that’s an okay to leave the world of What You See Is What You Get), onto Visual Basic (What) and Java (WHAT). They could learn JavaScript! There was Chrome installed on those computers! Those are basically IDEs for JavaScript! There’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://codepen.io/&#34;&gt;tons&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://jsfiddle.net/&#34;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pythontutor.com/javascript.html#mode=edit&#34;&gt;websites&lt;/a&gt; for live-coding with JavaScript! THEY WOULD NEVER HAVE TO HIT COMPILE. THEY ALREADY KNEW HTML AND CSS. Remembering this made me even sadder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I thought about how this probably wasn’t an isolated case. Hell, I recently wrote an “Introduction to Twitter” manual for teachers, even though Twitter is literally just public email with a character limit. There’s no way anyone had bothered to show them Google’s (flawed, but ambitious) “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs-first.com/en/why-cs&#34;&gt;CS First&lt;/a&gt;” and they thought anything but “Computers are scary”. That brought me to the edge of tears at the feeling of helplessness in the face of 25 years of wasted money and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at this point that I went for a walk to calm myself down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I’m so obsessed with and excessively emotional about teaching kids to think programmatically, is that before I knew how to program, I literally &lt;em&gt;did not understand math&lt;/em&gt;. I passed math and physics courses by memorizing the solution steps required and regurgitating them onto a page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I was taught to program in my first year of university, I understood that algorithms are just a description of the steps you used to solve a problem. These steps involved math, because math is how you describe relations between things. Math describing shapes was called geometry. Math describing relations between shapes, so you could manipulate them, was called vectorial algebra. Math describing relations between physical objects in the real world was called mechanical physics. Sums were just for-loops, functions were just ways of wrapping a series of one or more operations and plots were just tools to help you see what your math was doing. I had found the &lt;a href=&#34;http://worrydream.com/LadderOfAbstraction/&#34;&gt;Ladder of Abstraction&lt;/a&gt; along with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Divide_and_conquer_algorithms&#34;&gt;method of Divide and Conquer&lt;/a&gt; and it was beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I had revisited my old High School, I did a horribly thought-out presentation on my research. At one point I showed a displayed showing how neurons computed functions. A student exclaimed in horror: “NOT PLOTS. I HATE PLOTS. I CAN’T DO THEM.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their statement stopped me in my tracks. I had forgotten what it was like to think you had to “do” plots. That they weren’t just something that you used to gain insight into the world around me. I had forgotten what it was to “hate” the things you couldn’t understand instead of looking for different approaches to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst part is, this is the fault of me and my kin. The electrical engineers and computer scientists who built computing ecosystems so hostile they became feared and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.loper-os.org/?p=568&#34;&gt;created walled gardens that killed chances at creativity like Hypercard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the way out of this grave we’ve dug ourselves, I don’t have the arrogance of some my brethren to claim to know the solution to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0QFDzRkmiUE&#34;&gt;extremely contentious topic of education&lt;/a&gt;. All I wish to claim is that resources are being wasted. If you are a teacher and you want to use computers better in your classroom, please reach out to me. If I cannot help you, I will at least point you towards &lt;a href=&#34;http://hivewaterloo.ca/popup/hive-waterloo/&#34;&gt;someone&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kwartzlab.ca/&#34;&gt;who&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.diyode.com/&#34;&gt;can&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Nefarious Interconnectedness of Well-being</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2016-11-24-The-Nefarious-Interconnectedness-of-Well-being/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2016-11-24-The-Nefarious-Interconnectedness-of-Well-being/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[epistemic status: probably the cheesiest thing I’ve ever written and has probably been said better elsewhere]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The health center at the University of Waterloo has a bunch of workshops on dealing with stress. These are helpful workshops. The advice is pretty standard. Sleep, eat and exercise. Use Cognitive Behaviour Therapy to deal with unhelpful thought patterns. If you’ve got weird brain things going on, take some medication. However, the implementation details of these healthy habits aren’t given. This makes sense, because they’re super specific to the person, but it does give a person some weird expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also awkward to describe how interconnected all of these things are. You would be forgiven for thinking the progress towards a better life is linear:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  Why yes, graphic design is my passion. How did you know?
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/The-Nefarious-Interconnectedness-of-Well-being_0.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, you usually get something that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  Google Draw. Functional enough to get things done. Ugly enough that I wished I learned to use something else.
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/The-Nefarious-Interconnectedness-of-Well-being_1.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because instead of the progress on these things looking like a bunch of parallel branches:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  Look at all those nodes working together!
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/The-Nefarious-Interconnectedness-of-Well-being_2.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get some cluster-muffin like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  Oh noes. What happened nodes?
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/The-Nefarious-Interconnectedness-of-Well-being_3.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re lucky, there are solutions to all these things can be supported with a community that help you commit to the incremental process, but if you’re not as lucky you might get stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not the only person thinking about this. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clinicalneuropsychiatry.org/pdf/borsbooml.pdf&#34;&gt;Some clinicians&lt;/a&gt; think focusing treatment around a network of symptoms instead of a single diagnosis could lead to better treatment. I’m not a clinician, so I’m sure as hell not going to comment on the validity of that strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what the solution for this is. Managing food is getting easier, thanks to things like Soylent. I think &lt;a href=&#34;https://uwaterloo.ca/campus-wellness/counselling-services/uw-mates-peer-counselling&#34;&gt;Mates&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.7cups.com/&#34;&gt;7 Cups&lt;/a&gt; are trying to work towards students helping students so that everyone has a good community. Mostly, I just wanted to put this message out there, based on the belief that realistic expectations are beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recovery and coping is neither a uniform, nor a linear progression. Don’t expect it to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked this article and want to read more about psychological research and therapy, consider&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://uwaterloo.us15.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=d5612fe997cc72aac70c4ffe9&amp;amp;id=76226838bc&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;subscribing to my mailing list&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning isn’t the brain</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2016-11-17-Deep-Learning-isn-t-the-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2016-11-17-Deep-Learning-isn-t-the-brain/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;but-sometimes-the-results-look-like-one&#34;&gt;(but sometimes the results look like one)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[epistemic status: I work in a lab dedicated to biologically plausible neural circuits, so I’m informed on the problem, but probably still biased. There’s probably going be a follow-up post to this once I get a bunch of rebuttals from people smarter than me.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;As expected, I got a bunch of rebuttals and have&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@seanaubin/deep-learning-is-almost-the-brain-3aaecd924f3d&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;adjusted my position accordingly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2016/08/23/071076.full.pdf&#34;&gt;academic&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://timdettmers.com/2015/07/27/brain-vs-deep-learning-singularity/&#34;&gt;non-academic articles&lt;/a&gt; comparing Deep Learning (DL) and the brain. This offends my sensibilities a bit, because although there are &lt;a href=&#34;http://compneuro.uwaterloo.ca/publications/sharma2016b.html&#34;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/111/23/8619.abstract&#34;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; from DL that resembles certain areas of the brain, DL is not a good overall description of the brain. DL explicitly passes the buck on biological plausibility (like almost every other cognitive modelling approach) and implies that it’s “neurons” can be implemented biologically, it’s just that no one has bothered yet. I think the problem goes much deeper and that DL is missing a lot of the key features of the brain, which makes it a poor analogical target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-brain-is-low-power&#34;&gt;The brain is low power&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DL is power hungry. Alpha GO consumed the power of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tastehit.com/blog/google-deepmind-alphago-how-it-works/&#34;&gt;1202 CPUs and 176 GPUs&lt;/a&gt;, not to train, but &lt;em&gt;just to run&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudplatform.googleblog.com/2016/05/Google-supercharges-machine-learning-tasks-with-custom-chip.html&#34;&gt;TenserFlow Processing Unit&lt;/a&gt; is an attempt to satiate this hunger, but it’s still not even close to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cogsci.stackexchange.com/q/12750/4397&#34;&gt;brain’s power consumption of 20W&lt;/a&gt;. IBM’s TrueNorth chip is another example of trying to bring low-power computation, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@seanaubin/a-way-around-the-coming-performance-walls-neuromorphic-hardware-with-spiking-neurons-facd4291b201#.86xjo9oyf&#34;&gt;it’s capabilities are quite limited when compared to other Neuromorphic hardware&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically, True North only implements feed-forward networks and has no on-chip learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-brain-can-t-do-back-prop&#34;&gt;The brain can’t do back-prop&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back-propagation is the foundation of all DL. Although there is evidence that errors being propagated through multiple layers is happening in the brain, no one has come up with a method for back-propagation (back-prop)that doesn’t rely on information propagating backwards through unidirectional synapses. I personally think it’s only a matter of time before a biologically plausible method is discovered, but until then it is unwise to ignore the implementation details and the restrictions it might place on what can be learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-brain-uses-spikes-to-communicate&#34;&gt;The brain uses spikes to communicate&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is possible to &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1510.08829&#34;&gt;convert DL networks into spiking neurons for use on neuromorphic hardware&lt;/a&gt;, these spikes are not leveraged for specific computational advantages. As far as I know (and I still have some reading to do), spiking computation has yet to be used anywhere for the learning in DL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;neurotransmitters-aren-t-just-spike-transporters-and-neurons-aren-t-just-spike-machines&#34;&gt;Neurotransmitters aren’t just spike transporters and neurons aren’t just spike-machines&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DL completely ignores the role of neurotransmitters. However, neurotransmitters have been shown to be computationally significant in adapting the receptive features networks on the fly, something which DL has really hard time doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-brain-is-noisy&#34;&gt;The brain is noisy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the choice between neuron redundancy and neuron performance, evolution chose to make the brain redundant. &lt;a href=&#34;http://icwww.epfl.ch/~gerstner/SPNM/node33.html&#34;&gt;Neurons are noisy&lt;/a&gt;, which isn’t surprising when you consider the warm, biologically variable environment they’re in. Although certain DL networks can cope with loss of their nodes, DL isn’t known for it’s robustness to noisy input or noisy training data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, there are a lot of features of the brain that DL is omitting, thus using DL as an analogy for neural circuitry isn’t ideal. The alternative to comparing with DL is using a modelling paradigm that takes these challenges into account. At the time of writing, the only approach I know of is the Neural Engineering Framework (NEF) from the laboratory I belong to, but I’m sure as research marches forward other frameworks will emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But Sean,” you cry with a gleam of mischief in your eye, “don’t most NEF models from the lab you belong to suffer from the same problems as DL? The models usually stop at LIF neurons, which aren’t realistic neurons at all! Why don’t you use more complex neuron models, i.e. things like &lt;a href=&#34;http://pub.ist.ac.at/Pubs/courses/AY1314/MolandCellNeuro_S14/files/Stuart%20et%20al_Dendrites_Chapter16.pdf&#34;&gt;dendritic computation&lt;/a&gt;, multi-compartmental neurons, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cell.com/trends/immunology/abstract/S1471-4906%2815%2900200-8&#34;&gt;glial cells&lt;/a&gt; and neurogenesis?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a work in progress. There are 2 people (&lt;a href=&#34;http://compneuro.uwaterloo.ca/people/aaron-russell-voelker.html&#34;&gt;Aaron Voelker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://compneuro.uwaterloo.ca/people/peter-duggins.html&#34;&gt;Peter Duggins&lt;/a&gt;) of the 16-strong &lt;a href=&#34;http://compneuro.uwaterloo.ca/index.html&#34;&gt;Computation Neuroscience Research Group&lt;/a&gt; (CNRG) that I belong to who are working on the problem of more complex neuron models. &lt;a href=&#34;http://compneuro.uwaterloo.ca/people/eric-hunsberger.html&#34;&gt;Eric Hunsberger&lt;/a&gt; is working on biologically plausible back-prop and the moment he has a break-through you can be sure I’ll be shoving it in everyone’s face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for neurogenesis, There’s no good computational model of what neurogenesis does and the CNRG lacks the resources to do that sort of basic research. Dendritic and glial cell computation has no one working on it, because we’re only 16 people. If that bothers you, maybe you want to join us?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Surprising Things I Learned from Grad School</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2016-11-17-The-Surprising-Things-I-Learned-from-Grad-School/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2016-11-17-The-Surprising-Things-I-Learned-from-Grad-School/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been in grad school for a year now, so I figured now was as good of a time to reflect as ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot of things I expected to learn, like how to write a paper, what’s the difference between a conference paper and a journal paper and how do you get grants to support your research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also was totally blindsided by a lot of other things, which mostly fall into the categories “Computery Things” (because my lab develops a ton of software) and “Social Things”. If you only care about one of those categories, you can skip the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;writing-good-code-is-non-trivial&#34;&gt;Writing good code is non-trivial&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to think I was a pretty good coder. I left comments and I tried not duplicate code everywhere. Then I start having code-reviews whenever I submitted code to our big software project Nengo, where my lab-mates reviewed everything I had written and made suggestion. These code-reviews have taught me so much in terms of habits, setups and intuition that I couldn’t have gotten anywhere else. This kind of scares me, because it means I have no idea how non-computery labs are supposed to get better. Post snippets of their code on &lt;a href=&#34;http://codereview.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;codereview.stackexchange.com&lt;/a&gt;? Walk down the hall to the computer science department and force them to sit down with you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;dev-ops-is-foundational&#34;&gt;Dev Ops is foundational&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any successful commercial software project to be able to evolve, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000043.html&#34;&gt;the amount of time required for a new developer to get from interest to running code should be minimal&lt;/a&gt;. Not only that, but you should be able to log bugs, automatically run minimal tests and be able to quickly get the most updated code. All of these things fall under the umbrella of “Dev Ops”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dev Ops being important doesn’t stop being true when you’re a scientist writing scientific code, which is tragic because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dev Ops is freaking &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; You have to learn a bunch of different tools that haven’t been made non-hacker friendly yet. Travis-CI, whatever testing framework and builder your language uses (if it’s Matlab, good luck), and git (&lt;em&gt;shudder)&lt;/em&gt; suddenly go from become things you’ve heard of to things you need to understand &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dev Ops isn’t taught &lt;em&gt;anywhere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Not in Software Carpentry, Coursera and definitely not at your institution, so you need to wrangle together a bunch of tutorials from the Internet and sacrifice a mouse to the computer gods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these obstacles, it’s not surprising to learn that Dev Ops in scientific code is practically unheard of, even in widely distributed and used libraries. Before my Master’s degree I would have shrugged it off has not being a major problem in science, but now &lt;a href=&#34;https://bullshit.ist/why-im-an-open-source-nerd-an-apology-7d7a3e0e13e9#.f8rjqga4h&#34;&gt;I scream in horror&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;centralized-documentation-is-life-support&#34;&gt;Centralized documentation is life support&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having your documentation to your project somewhere online, where anyone can propose edits, is the only way your project’s docs will remain up to date and thus the only way your software will be able to proliferate and survive. Luckily, unlike everything else in this article, there’s tons of solutions to this! I just don’t know which one to recommend to absolute beginners… Leave a comment and I’ll update this section?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;scientific-tooling-is-horrible&#34;&gt;Scientific tooling is horrible&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of keeping up with research is reading a lot of papers. I thought for sure there would be tools for this everywhere. A unified program (I use a bunch of separate ones) that lets you tag papers, then search through the tags and annotations. A website where you can subscribe to feeds on research you’re interested in (lots of those exist) and collaboratively comment (nope) on publications. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YuGVC8VqXz0&amp;amp;list=WL&amp;amp;index=45&#34;&gt;Interactive drawing/coding tools&lt;/a&gt; for making complex animated figures. A thriving StackExchange where researchers bounce ideas off each other and drive synthesis of new concepts. Nope. Instead you get ResearchGate, Twitter, Mendeley, Google Draw and spam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


  
    &lt;figure &gt;
  



  &lt;label for=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
  

  
  Follow me on Twitter for more hilarious insights into why things are horrible.
  
  
  

  &lt;/span&gt;


  
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/img/The-Surprising-Things-I-Learned-from-Grad-School_0.png&#34; &gt;
  



&lt;/figure&gt;




  &lt;/section&gt;

    
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;your-team-is-essential&#34;&gt;Your team is essential&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lab-mates are important. I knew they were important, but I didn’t know just &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; important. Without my lab-mate Aaron, I would have never published my first paper. Without my lab-mate Terry, I would have never been able to determine the appropriate scope for my initial research for that paper. Without my lab-mate Trevor, I would have never learned how to write good scientific software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;communicating-concepts-is-excavation&#34;&gt;Communicating concepts is excavation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to think of myself as a pretty good communicator. I even put it on my resume. However, this year all evidence that I had of that was utterly and irrevocably refuted. This year was the year I learned Non-Violent Communication, which taught me how to talk about emotions and has literally changed my life, but that’s a whole other blog post. This was also the year where I routinely needed to quickly grasp concepts and relate them to my current knowledge so I could remember the faint outline of their importance for later. This technical communication style did not come easily for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s are a few tricks I use when teaching or learning from other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Useful questions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What’s the last thing you understood?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can you say what I just said back to me, but using different words?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the closest thing that you think you know to this concept?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What do you mean by… ? What did you think I meant by… ?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When meeting with someone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be specific about what you need from them: “I want your help deciding… ?”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make sure you both leave with the same conclusion: “What I’m going to remember from this is… ? Is this what you wanted me to remember?”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post-doc in my lab, Terry Stewart, has this down to an art form. To the point that I frequently like to watch him teach concepts to people just to see how he manoeuvres through their understanding like a hawk through a canyon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, I still need to work on my similes and metaphors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;mathematical-notation-is-a-foreign-language&#34;&gt;Mathematical notation is a foreign language&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I currently have no idea how to communicate with mathematical concepts textually. I literally have to translate them from/to code. I learned this during my undergrad, where math made sense to me for the first time in my life after I learned how to program. However, I only realised serious it was this semester. I look at a sum and I think “Okay, a for-loop”. I see a chain of equations and I think “Where’s the source code?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, unless I’ve programmed something, like back-prop or the Neural Engineering Framework. I cannot say I truly understand it. This is a bit problematic at the moment, given my immense confusion with the following things which I need to rectify in the next 7 months and I’m not sure they’re easy to code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partially Observable Markov Decision Processes. What are those things?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How does Theano/TensorFlow work (specifically the actual symbolic tree parsing and graph creation) and are they as impossible debug as I fear?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How do Restricted Boltzmann Machines use Monte-Carlo Markov-Chains to optimise themselves?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What’s the relation between Tang’s work on combining factors from different Deep Learning networks and disentangling factor variation?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How can statistical machine learning methods like SVM and Bayesian Networks be used to train Deep Learning networks?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why is sensor fusion still such a big, open topic?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wish me luck.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Now and The Dangers of Bullshit</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2016-09-15-The-Power-of-Now-and-The-Dangers-of-Bullshit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2016-09-15-The-Power-of-Now-and-The-Dangers-of-Bullshit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[epistemic status: a structured, but ultimately somewhat ranty warning against self-help books and their bullshit with the hope of saving others time]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a time in my life when everything sucked, so I started to read self-help books, based off of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.raptitude.com/2013/02/five-self-help-books-that-actually-helped/&#34;&gt;this list from Raptitude&lt;/a&gt;. The first book off that list was “This is How”, which along for “Man’s Search for Meaning” is one of the most inspirational books I’ve ever read. The second one was “The Power of Now” (TPN) which I simultaneously loved (sharing verses with my friends and family) and hated (literally screaming out loud in agony after reading some sentences). There is no denying the author writes excellent practical prose. Unfortunately, he doesn’t stick to applied mindfulness and veers off into pseudo-profound bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TPN is a classic among self-help books and it’s easy to see why given its parallels to Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT) which &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@seanaubin/debugging-your-thoughts-with-mind-maps-94aeecd2821d#.96p14ixwy&#34;&gt;I’m a big fan of&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like CBT, TPN encourages you to identify unhelpful, repetitive thought patterns and assess their usefulness to the present state. Does calling yourself a failure and a disappointment actually help you perform better or does it just make you afraid to try? What happens if you stop focusing on those labels and instead focus on systematically what you can do to perform better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TPN also encourages being aware of emotions, as an indication of thoughts you might not be recognising. If you immediately tense when entering a meeting, maybe you should review if that reaction is sensible or helpful. Where is it coming from? What thought or belief triggers it? Do you think that you are unable to get any idea across in when there are more than two people involved?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, TPN makes an explicit distinction between worrying and dwelling versus planning and learning from the past. TPN urges you to either take action or if this is not possible, schedule to take action later. Whatever you do, don’t hold it in you head and waste precious processing resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, so good! And then comes the bullshit…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;II.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullshit has been defined delightfully by Frankurt in his book &lt;em&gt;On Bullshit&lt;/em&gt;. However, &lt;a href=&#34;http://journal.sjdm.org/15/15923ac/jdm15923acr.pdf&#34;&gt;my favourite definition of bullshit comes from Gordon Pennycook&lt;/a&gt;, who defines bullshit as being “ something that is constructed without concern for the truth. By this definition, bullshit statements can be true, false, or meaningless. The absence or presence of these factors is irrelevant to something being bullshit. Nonetheless, although bullshit statements can be incidentally true, bullshit is generally false and hence, often problematic.” Pennycook also emphasises how it’s generally “design[ed] to impress”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is usually seen in pseudo-science or spirituality (Deepak Chopra is a great example), where the words “toxins”, “forces”, “consciousness” and “organic” are stripped of their scientific meaning and used to give illusions of grandeur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst part is, it’s partly our fault as science communicators for falling for the easy metaphor that helps spread this bullshit. Consequently, I hereby urge myself and other scientists to consider the following before using a metaphor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indicate the limitations of the metaphor and its motivation. What are you trying to give a feel for? What does this feel explain and what doesn’t it explain?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Give directions to opportunities for more in depth knowledge. Whether this be other articles or StackExchange Communities specialising in that form of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Highlight the limits of current scientific knowledge and why the field is still being pursued.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But I have a limited space of text to dedicate to the spread of knowledge!” I know and the fact that &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@seanaubin/mind-maps-for-augmented-thinking-communication-24a7d949388d#.673ghom5w&#34;&gt;we haven’t invented a better form of communication given the advent of computers&lt;/a&gt; may be one of humanities greatest tragedies. But until humanity gets its act together, we might as well face the reality that text is still a dominant communication medium and accept the responsibility to use it as effectively and safely as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool. I’m glad we’ve got that sorted out, now let’s go back to TPN for some practical examples of bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;III.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TPN is a repeat offender of spreading pseudo-profound bullshit in its second half, which is weird since its first half is so practical. It’s like the author wrote the first part talking to people about their problems and the second half while tripping on acid. They go from giving actionable suggestions to unleashing an avalanche of meaningless buzzwords in the space of one chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, butchering theoretical physics while talking about meditation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also raises the vibrational frequency of the energy field that gives life to the physical body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then using this bullshit to justify magical thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more consciousness you direct into the inner body, the higher its vibrational frequency becomes, much like a light that grows brighter as you turn up the dimmer switch and so increase the flow of electricity . At this higher energy level , negativity cannot affect you anymore, and you tend to attract new circumstances that reflect this higher frequency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making hilariously general claims about consciousness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything that exists has Being, has God-essence, has some degree
of consciousness. Even a stone has rudimentary consciousness;
otherwise, it would not be, and its atoms and molecules would
disperse. Everything is alive. The sun, the earth, plants, animals,
humans — all are expressions of consciousness in varying degrees,
consciousness manifesting as form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dismissing the Scientific method as confirmation bias:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When scientists study space, they usually make it into something and thereby miss its essence entirely . Not surprisingly , the latest theory is that space isn’t empty at all , that it is filled with some substance. Once you have a theory , it’s not too hard to find evidence to substantiate it, at least until some other theory comes along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grouping anti-depressants with alcohol:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it weren’t for alcohol, tranquillisers, antidepressants, as well as the illegal drugs, which are all consumed in vast quantities, the insanity of the human mind would become even more glaringly obvious than it is already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claiming that meditation can cure all illnesses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a simple but powerful self-healing meditation that you can do
whenever you feel the need to boost your immune system. It is
particularly effective if used when you feel the first symptoms of an
illness, but it also works with illnesses that are already entrenched if
you use it at frequent intervals and with an intense focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one common thread in all these examples; they don’t mean/explain anything. They have no basis in evidence, don’t help you learn from your past or avoid pitfalls in your future and give you no further avenues for investigation, all while crowding out more helpful explanations. They are purest bullshit and should be addressed as so, by dismissing them in their entirety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, all of my concerns with TPN come down to the spread of bullshit. TPN aims to impress and empower with these passages without concern for their outside damage. I can only hope that the readers of TPN are more mindful than its author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked this article and want to read more book reviews and summaries of psychological therapeutic research, consider&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://uwaterloo.us15.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=d5612fe997cc72aac70c4ffe9&amp;amp;id=76226838bc&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;subscribing to my mailing list&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why “Learning Night” Works</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2016-09-10-Why-Learning-Night-Works/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2016-09-10-Why-Learning-Night-Works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been running &lt;a href=&#34;https://learningnight.com/&#34;&gt;Learning Night&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Waterloo (LNUW) with the help of Christina Tan for around a year now and I think it’s safe to say it’s “working”. We have people that come to every night. We have new people every night that seem to react positively. There are new and challenging ideas that are discussed at least once a semester. People are learning new things. We’ve managed to keep it free and open to anyone. And unsurprisingly, we are totally unable to scale beyond 30 people, despite extensive recruitment efforts via conferences, other talks and Tinder. So why does “Learning Night” work, specifically at the University of Waterloo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not the speakers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, the speakers we’ve been getting at LNUW are great. They tell us about their talks ahead of time, they do their best to prepare, are receptive to feedback and we love them. But Christina and I are not that well connected and Waterloo is not Florence during Renaissance. Most of our speakers are students who don’t have that much free time and don’t have that much life experience yet, compared to the other Learning Nights in San Francisco, Mountain View and Toronto. If LNUW suddenly changed from “You don’t have to be experienced, just enthusiastic” to “Experts only please” we would find approximately one speaker per semester and we would probably have to pay them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not the people&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear, LNUW attendees, can be forthright with you? I love you folks. You are the social light in my mostly academic life. However, I think we can all agree that you can still love someone with all your heart despite that from the outside world’s perspective the receiver of your affections totally ordinary. The participants of LNUW are just undergrads, grads and other people working in the community. Some of them run startups, some of them are award-winning scientists and this is all exciting, but we certainly aren’t composed of Nobel Prize Winners, Worldwide Critically Acclaimed Artists or The Next Mark/Bill Zuckerberg/Gates. The organisers are also remarkably ordinary. &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@seanaubin/how-i-got-here-failures-privileges-and-luck-9f35ea119420#.hivsh8ixo&#34;&gt;I’m a second-rate grad student&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eloquentspeaking.com/&#34;&gt;Christina runs a public speaking startup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s the community structure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only reason LNUW works is because we have the resources to scaffold a community together. Everyone turns off their phones and have come to learn, so it’s not like people are begrudgingly attending a lecture. It’s established that questions guiding people is okay, so it’s not a bad thing if you aren’t the world expert on your topic or you get a little lost. We have somewhere to meet afterwards, which means that if you want to have an intense conversation with one of the speakers on a topic, you don’t have to awkwardly schedule a coffee date later. We have events that we go to together, so it’s not like we are mono-culturally The Learning People. If you want to keep in touch with someone from LNUW, just post events on the Facebook page that other people can attend. Finally, we’ve kept LNUW free and unassociated to any type of corporate interest to emphasise as clearly as possible that the only reason that this exists if for friends to share ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Night isn’t magic. It can work almost anywhere and when I talk to people, it does seem that this type of thing has risen organically in groups of friends many times in the past. I also don’t think this is the only way to run it, nor that it will always be run this way. However, I do think these principles are valuable and I hope these lessons can be transferred to other communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Universal Basic Income: A Divide</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2016-08-21-Universal-Basic-Income-A-Divide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2016-08-21-Universal-Basic-Income-A-Divide/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[epistemic status: opinion piece with a plea for skepticism from someone with a very poor understanding of economics]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2017/04/conversation-basic-income-mess-heres-make-sense.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;there is now&lt;/em&gt; ****** &lt;em&gt;excellent analysis of the various economic proposals that carry the name of Universal Basic Income over at Naked Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@seanaubin/mind-maps-for-augmented-thinking-communication-24a7d949388d#.bghupl3xd&#34;&gt;As I’ve written elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, labels are useful as a compressed representation for quickly assessing common ground (“You’re a Brony too!?!”), but they can also just cause annoying divisions (“How can you be a feminist/Muslim?!?”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like this is currently happening with Universal Basic Income (UBI). The label is being thrown around, but there’s actually two different meanings that I’ll give labels to for compression reasons. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/jun/22/silicon-valley-universal-basic-income-y-combinator&#34;&gt;One side is talking about replacing social services with UBI and sees UBI as freedom to unleash your inner entrepreneur&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s calls these people the Silicos. The other side wants UBI to fill the gaps that the social services can’t satisfy and freedom from the need for constant competition. Let’s call them the concerned Utopians. I’m part of the latter and I feel this position needs to be made distinct from the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concerned Utopian knows that we’re getting close to the world we dreamed of technologically, but socially we screwed up hard somewhere along the way. We have automation doing a lot of the boring labour and we have a network of free information at our fingertips, but we also have increasingly powerful corporations, rampant destructive consumerism and miserable joblessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a concerned Utopian, we look at these problems, some on the horizon and many of which are already here, and we wonder about solutions. Money seems like a problem and giving it away seems like a solution. Getting the money by taxing the gains from automation and stopping this whole college/university clustermuffin also seems like a good idea. This idealist view is exemplified perfectly by Scott Alexander in this passage from “&lt;a href=&#34;http://slatestarcodex.com/2014/05/23/ssc-gives-a-graduation-speech/&#34;&gt;SSC Give A Graduation Speech&lt;/a&gt;”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… consider your life on a $20,000 a year income guarantee. No longer tied down to a job, you can live wherever you want. I love the mountains. Let’s live in a cabin in Colorado, way up in the Rockies. You can find stunningly beautiful ones for $500 a month — freed from the mad rush to get into scarce urban or suburban areas with good school districts, housing is actually really cheap. So there you are in the Rockies, maybe with a used car to take you to Denver when you want to see people or go to a show, but otherwise all on your own except for the deer and squirrels. You wake up at nine, cook yourself a healthy breakfast, then take a long jog out in the forest. By the time you come back, you’ve got a lot of interesting thoughts, and you talk about them with the dozens of online friends you cultivate close relationships with and whom you can take a road trip and visit any time you feel like. Eventually you’re talked out, and you curl up with a good book — this week you’re trying to make it through Aristotle on aesthetics. The topic interests you since you’re learning to paint — you’ve always wanted to be an artist, and with all the time in the world and stunning views to inspire you, you’re making good progress. Freed from the need to appeal to customers or critics, you are able to develop your own original style, and you take heart in the words of the old Kipling poem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And none but the Master will praise them
And none but the Master will blame
And no one will work for money
And no one will work for fame
But each for the joy of the working
Each on his separate star
To draw the thing as he sees it
For the God of things as they are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fans of your work is a cute girl — this time I’m assuming you’re a man, I’m sure over the past four years you’ve learned some choice words for people who do that. You date and get married. She comes to live with you — she’s also getting $20,000 a year from the government in place of an education, so now you’re up to $40,000, which is actually very close to the US median household income. You have two point four kids. With both of you at home full time, you see their first steps, hear their first words, get to see them as they begin to develop their own personalities. They start seeming a little lonely for other kids their own age, so with a sad good-bye to your mountain, you move to a bigger house in a little town on the shores of a lake in Montana. There’s no schooling for them, but you teach them to read, first out of children’s books, later out of something a little harder like Harry Potter, and then finally you turn them loose in your library. Your oldest devours your collection of Aristotle and tells you she wants to be a philosopher when she grows up. Evenings they go swimming, or play stickball with the other kids in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they reach college age, your daughter is so thrilled at the opportunity to learn from her intellectual heroes that she goes to Chase-Bear-Goldman-Sallie-Manhattan-Stearns-Sachs-Mae-FEDGOV and asks for a loan. They’re happy to give her fifteen thousand, which is all college costs nowadays — only the people who are really interested in learning feel the need to go nowadays, and supply so outpaces demand that prices are driven down. She makes it into Yale (unsurprising given how much better home-schooled students do) studies philosophy, but finds she likes technology better. She decides to become an engineer, and becomes part of the base of wealthy professionals helping fund the income guarantee for everyone else. She marries a nice man &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; making sure he’s willing to stay home and take care of the children — she’s not crazy, she doesn’t want to send them to some kind of &lt;em&gt;institution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your younger son, on the other hand, is a little intellectually disabled and can’t read above a third-grade level. That’s not a big problem for you or for him. When he grows older, he moves to Hawaii where he spends most of his time swimming in the ocean and by all accounts enjoys himself very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re happy your son will be financially secure for the rest of his life, but on a broader scale, you’re happy that no one around you has to live in fear of getting fired, or is struggling to make ends meet, or is stuck in the Rust Belt with a useless skill set. Every so often, you call your daughter and thank her for helping design the robots that do most of the hard work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how there’s no mention of anyone trying to start their own startup? No trying to out-consume the neighbours? This vision seems alien to the Silicos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, this is almost recklessly idealist, but luckily concerned Utopians are not &lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; stupid. We know that giving away money doesn’t solve every problem. There’s still a lot of social services that need to exist because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coordinating a community to provide every service it needs, even when no one has jobs, is really hard.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;People have really weird varying levels of health that totally isn’t their fault.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;etc…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are things governments can be good at. The Silicos disagree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the concerned Utopian veers off from the left-leaning, but inevitably heartless libertarian. They seem to believe that Universal Basic Income can replace social services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I think condemning or embracing the whole idea of UBI is bad, since there seems to be a wide variety of approaches. Coming up with a new name for it would be good, but is also annoying, because labels suck. Sceptically assessing each claim of UBI (in terms of it’s implementation and transition period), until we find one that fits our concerned Utopian ideals and the championing the hell out of it, is better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: How to Read a Book</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/2016-07-30-Book-Review-How-to-Read-a-Book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/2016-07-30-Book-Review-How-to-Read-a-Book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started read “How to Read a Book” by Adler Mortimer (HRB) after one of the engineers I look up to, &lt;a href=&#34;http://starsimpson.com/&#34;&gt;Star Simpson&lt;/a&gt;, professed that her ability to understand many technical papers resulted from the instruction contained therein. As someone who’s desperately trying to hack their way to understanding the field of Cognitive Science via intense reading, I figured trying to polish the art of what I was doing every day is time well spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HRB starts out the way most self-help books do, describing the writer’s own ascent for ignorance to enlightenment. Basically, Adler graduates from university thinking he knows everything. He doesn’t and is distressed. He realises he’s never really “read”, he’s only let information flow through him without connecting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this relatable intro, Adler descends into a rant about the current education system’s failures in the context of “reading”. If you are actually interested in educational reform, read “The Educated Mind” by Kieran Egan, which is way better written and actually provides many practical solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this book is quite lengthy and repetitive. Maybe that’s just how books were written those days? Or maybe the author was actually afraid of the readers leaving his grasp without any progress? As a result, I gave up after finishing Part II, since he begins addressing fiction and specific books for the rest of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, below is a summary of what Adler considers “reading” and the various techniques required to be a “reader”, instead of just a “consumer”. I’ve tried to make more hacker-friendly than &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_to_Read_a_Book&#34;&gt;the Wikipedia summary&lt;/a&gt; and the summary table included in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The techniques can be divided into three “readings” or as prefer to call them “perspectives”, which are each in turn divided into four “rules” or more understandably “approaches”. Each “approach” is to be done continuously while reading the book to aid understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Analytical Perspective (top-down)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Classify the book. What is it’s focus?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summarise the book. What is the most important content of this book?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summarise all the parts (this division might be chapters or more arbitrary divisions). How do each of the parts contribute to the whole?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What problems is the author trying to solve?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Interpretive Perspective (bottom-up)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are the important words that the author is defining?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How does the author define these concepts in phrases? What about paragraphs?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How do the paragraphs support the author’s arguments?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are the author’s arguments? Can you imagine instances where they hold true?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Critical Perspective (ways you can disagree with the author)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Show where the author is uninformed. Where are they lacking information?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Show where the author is misinformed. Where have they poorly interpreted the information given?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Show where the author is illogical. Where are the gaps in their reasoning?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Find when to withhold judgement due to insufficient evidence, but please define what evidence you would need to be convinced and evaluate if that is reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have already known some of these rules before reading this text, however it is nice to have it describe in one place systematically. For example this systematisation, highlights that criticising the work is the final step. You must understand what the author is doing and how they can hold this world-view. Only then can you truly understand whether it needs to be corrected and in what ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual rules for learning a skill still apply. Don’t try to do them all at once. Try each technique individually and see how you can make it work. Eventually, you’ll be able to do them simultaneously with less effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these instructions aren’t clear enough, then by all means download the PDF and plough through it. However, since life is short, skip Part B where he rambles on about education, which are of no benefit to someone who’s trying to figure out how to “read”. Additionally, be prepared to be beaten over the head repeatedly with basic concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;II.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from these rambles on education and these helpful “reading” techniques, Adler also spends a considerable amount of time expounding the benefits of Great Books. He means “reading” classics and associating them together to gain a complete understanding of humanity’s knowledge and it’s epistemology. He claims that to understand any field, one must go to the primary discoverers and read their publications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sympathetic to this point of view. Computer Science has failed miserably as a field because we fail to acknowledge the lessons taught to us by those who came before. For examples of this, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FvmTSpJU-Xc&#34;&gt;this video by Alan Kay&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/71278954&#34;&gt;this other video by Brett Viktor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I can’t seem to resolve the idea that one should totally ground themselves philosophically before proceeding experimentally when I’ve wasted countless hours researching when I really should have just built something. For example, when I was first learning to program and when I thought optogenetics were the future of brain-computer interfaces. Surely there is some middle ground, where you focus on what interests you and maintain a group of colleagues with diverse interests to divert you if you’ve ignored some piece of prior art?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adler proceeds to irritate me further by claiming that anyone else but the primary discoverer is unsuited for teaching:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, in the same college, two men were lecturing, one a man who had discovered some truth, the other a man who was repeating secondhand what he had heard reported of the first man’s work, which would you rather go to hear? Yes, even supposing that the repeater promised to make it a little simpler by talking down to your level, would you not suspect that the secondhand stuff lacked something in quality or quantity? If you paid the greater price in effort, you would be rewarded by better goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that the quality of materials, nor the quality of mentorship matters not for teaching:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great books can be read in or out of school. If they are read in school, in classes under the supervision of live teachers, the latter must properly subordinate themselves to the dead ones. We can learn only from our intellectual betters. The great books are better than most living teachers as well as their students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I can understand where Adler is coming from, a world where materials are limited and expensive to spread, I don’t think it holds up to the current reality. A primary discover is nothing compared to someone who &lt;a href=&#34;http://worrydream.com/SomeThoughtsOnTeaching/&#34;&gt;must use the knowledge every day&lt;/a&gt;, thus knowing it’s limitations intimately in the context of the present day. A book is nothing compared to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://explorableexplanations.com/&#34;&gt;Explorable Explanation&lt;/a&gt;, where you can see the gears that formed the idea in the first place and manipulate them to make new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bring up this counter-argument, not because I think Adler should have invented time-travel to see the advent of the Internet, but because I feel like I still feel the echoes of this appeal to intellectualism on a day to day basis. Whether it’s Cognitive Neuroscientists using statistics as black box and then &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/113/28/7900.abstract&#34;&gt;paying the price&lt;/a&gt; when it turns out their “intellectual betters” are still fumbly humans, or when I find a group of students recoil in fear at the mention of a plot because they don’t know that it’s a tool for visualisation: context matters, ideas evolve and the transparency of the reasoning you leave behind dictate the innovations that will proceed from your discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;III.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you need to read a bunch of things and you get the feeling you’re not quite doing it right, by all means, read HRB. However, after you’ve felt first-hand the limitations of print, remember that humanity is capable of so much more and it’s your responsibility as an innovator to strive for it in any way you can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>